Finding Aid for Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History collection, 1950-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History collection 1950-1997
Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History.
(in 24 boxes)
17 linear feet
2010198 Bi 2
Records of the organization as well as collections of records received from individuals and organization relating to the development and history of special education in Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Regional Education Resource Center of Saginaw Valley State University (donor no. 10422 ) in October 2010.
The collection is open to research.
The Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History (SPMSEH) was formed in 1988 by a group of individuals who were concerned that the history of special education in Michigan be known and that the source material for the study of this history be preserved. The organization was governed by a board of directors and met at the annual convention of the Michigan Council for Exceptional Children and the Summer Institute of the Michigan Association of Administrators of Special Education. One of the aims of the organization was to establish an archive and library of materials relating to special education. To this end, several special education leaders and administrators donated a variety of materials to the organization. These included Richard Baldwin who was Director of Office of Special Education, Michigan Department of Education in 1996 and long-time executive secretary of the SPMSEH; Arselia Sehler Ensign, member of the Michigan Special Education Advisory Committee; Robert Luce, one-time president Michigan Federation Chapters, Council for Exceptional Children, legislative chair of the Saginaw Chapter of CEC, and director of special education of the Midland Intermediate School District; and Irene Gromek, who was with the Macomb Intermediate School District. The organization dissolved in 2001 and the materials that had been collected turned over to the Saginaw Valley State University and maintained as the Michigan Special Education History Archive. These materials were donated to the Bentley Historical Library in 2010.
The records of the Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History include both records of the organization (minutes, newsletters, mailing, etc.) as well as materials collected from individuals active in the field of special education. Some of the materials were clearly identified as belonging to either Richard Baldwin, Arselia Sehler Ensign, and Robert Luce and were kept together as separate series. Other materials, less clearly defined, were arranged by the organization or agency that created them. The kinds of documents in the collection include reports, minutes of meetings, newsletters, educational manuals, directives from the Michigan Department of Education and other agencies, copies and analyses of legislation under consideration by the state legislature, policy statements, and memoranda and correspondence.
The series in the record group include: Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History organization records; Richard Baldwin papers; Arselia Sheler Ensign papers; Robert Luce papers; Michigan Federation Chapters of the Council for Exceptional Children; Michigan Association of Administrators of Special Education; Michigan School for the Blind; Statewide Communication and Dissemination System; Citizens Alliance to Uphold Special Education; Physically Impaired Association of Michigan; Statewide Technical Assistance Network in Special Education; Local planning and instructional manuals; and Published material.
Subjects:
Citizens Alliance to Uphold Special Education.; Council for Exceptional Children.; Council for Exceptional Children. Michigan Federation Chapters.; Michigan. Dept. of Education.; Michigan Association of Administrators of Special Education.; Michigan School for the Blind.; Physically Impaired Association of Michigan.; Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History.; Statewide Communication and Dissemination System.; Statewide Technical Assistance Network in Special Education.; Exceptional children--Michigan.; Special education--Michigan.
Contributors:
Baldwin, Richard L.; Ensign, Arselia Sehler.; Luce, Robert.
- Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History organization records
  - Early record 1988-1989, 27 folders (in 1 expandable folder) (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors and Committee Chairs record books
    (include minutes and agenda, memos, budget material and related)
    - Harrold Spicknall volume circa 1990-1997 (Box 1)
    - Bruce Johnson volume circa 1988-1995 (Box 1)
    - Gene Thurber volume circa 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Handbooks 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, programs, and introductory information 1989-1997 (Box 1)
  - Scattered minutes and membership material 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of special education children and teachers (Box 1)
- Richard Baldwin papers
  - Reports, memoranda
    - 1950-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1993 (Box 3)
  - Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History (SPMSEH)
    - Meeting Minutes 9/27/1988-3/05/1991 (Box 3)
    - Articles of Incorporation, Tax Exempt Status (Box 3)
    - Oral History Notes, Consent Forms (Box 3)
    - Finance 1991-1993 (Box 3)
    - Undated Materials (Box 3)
  - Mandatory Special Education in Michigan: Assessment and Recommendations 1977 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Visiting Teacher Program 1954-1965 (Box 4)
  - Movement Teaching 1967 (Box 4)
  - Institute for the Achievement of Human Potential May 11-14, 1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Harold Spicknall Litigation/Task Force 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Nondiscrimination in Federally Assisted Programs 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Michigan School for the Blind History 1977-1981 (Box 4)
- Arselia Sehler Ensign papers
  - Correspondence 1967-1993 General Early State Dept.-Pre Media Center (Box 5)
  - Annual Program Plan 1977, 1981 Michigan Dept. of Education (Box 5)
  - Barrier Free Access (Box 5)
  - Blindness-Speeches (Box 5)
  - Braille Speed Reading, Special Studies Institute July 2-13, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Braille Transcription (Box 5)
  - C.A.U.S.E.-Citizens Alliance to Uphold Special Education (Box 5)
  - Cerebral Palsy (Box 5)
  - Construction Code (Box 5)
  - Education for all Handicapped Children, P.L. 94-142 of 1975 (Box 6)
  - Elementary & Secondary Education Act P. L. 91-230, 93-380; E.S.E.A. of 1965 Title VI P.L. 89-750 (Box 6)
  - Emotionally Disturbed Children (Box 6)
  - Fire & Safety for the Handicapped Committee, Technical (Sub) Committee; Michigan School Fire & Safety Rules (Box 6)
  - Fire & Safety for the Handicapped, Sub-Committee of State Architectural Accessibility Advisory Committee (Box 6)
  - Hearing Impaired (Deaf & Hard of Hearing) (Box 6)
  - Homebound & Hospitalized Program; Visiting Teachers (Box 6)
  - Housing/Independent Living (Box 6)
  - Instructional Materials (Box 6)
  - Learning Disabilities (Box 6)
  - Legislation-Barrier Free Access; Michigan Center for a Barrier Free Environment (Box 7)
  - Mandatory Special Education in Michigan P.A. 198 of 1971 (Box 7)
  - Initiative Petition for Mandatory Special Education. Citizen's Committee for Mandatory Special Education 2/3/1971 (Box 7)
  - A Monitoring Model for the Evaluation of Special Education Programs & Service, Kalamazoo Valley Intermediate School District 1978 (Box 7)
  - Mental Retardation
    - General (Box 7)
    - P.L. 85-926, Amended 1969 Consultants Panel, USOE Bur. of Educ. For the Handicapped, Div. of Training Programs (Box 7)
    - Undated Materials (Box 7)
  - Michigan School for the Blind
    - 1966-1970, undated Materials (Box 8)
    - 1971 (Box 8)
  - Michigan School for the Deaf (Box 8)
  - Movement & Mobility; Creative Movement-Macomb Intermediate School District (Box 8)
  - Movement & Mobility Impaired-Multiple Sclerosis, Muscular Dystrophy (Box 8)
  - Multiply Handicapped (Box 8)
  - Occupational Therapy (Box 8)
  - Orthopedic Programs & Teachers (Box 8)
  - Parents of the Handicapped (Box 9)
  - Planning (Box 9)
  - Planning Institute, G.O. Institute, Toward a Goal Oriented Curriculum for the Physically Handicapped November 21-24, 1971 (Box 9)
  - P.O.H.I. (Physically & Otherwise Health Impaired), C.O.H.I. (Crippled & Other Health Impaired) (Box 9)
  - P.O.H.I. Presentation Guidelines: Supportive Services Committee 1973 (August-September), Programs for the Physical & Otherwise Health Impaired (POHI) (Box 9)
  - P.O.H.I.-Teacher Certification (Box 9)
  - Recreation & Physical Education
    - Indian Trails Camp (Box 9)
    - Handicap Forum 3/22/1973 (Box 9)
  - Social Services (Box 10)
  - Special Education-Administration
    - Admin. Rules Summer Institute- 1986 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Assn. of Administrators of Special Educ., Special Educ. Supervisors, State Education Agency Simulation Exercise 1971 (Box 10)
    - Contact Persons (Box 10)
    - History (Box 10)
  - Special Education
    - Code (Michigan), P.A. 198 of 1971 (Box 10)
    - Program Directories (Box 10)
    - Programs
      - Administrative Guides (Box 10)
      - State Plans (Box 10)
      - Statistics (Box 10)
    - Services-Michigan Department of Education, Annual Reports (Box 10)
  - Speech (Speaking) Problems (Box 11)
  - Teacher Competencies (Box 11)
  - Teacher Consultants (Box 11)
  - Workshop-Communication Enhancement Institute 1976 (Box 11)
  - Workshop-Professional Preparation for Educators of Crippled Children 1970 (Box 11)
  - Teachers (Box 12)
  - Transportation (Box 12)
  - Visually Impaired
    - General (Box 12)
    - Infant Programs (Box 12)
    - Instructional Materials (Box 12)
    - Low Vision Training (Box 13)
    - Preschool Programs (Box 13)
    - Teacher Competencies (Box 13)
  - Vocational Education (Box 13)
  - Vocational Rehabilitation
    - Employment (Box 13)
    - An Introduction to the Estimated Disabled Population for Comprehensive Planning, Don Galvin 196? (Box 13)
    - Youth Occupational and Life Adjustment Manual Thomas F. Howard 1961 (Box 13)
  - Abstract for Ph.D. Degree (Box 13)
- Robert Luce papers
  - Michigan Federation Chapters of the Council for Exceptional Children
    - Constitution and revisions 1964-1983 (Box 14)
    - Annual business meeting minutes 1982-1987 (Box 14)
    - Executive Board meeting minutes 1964, 1969-1985 (Box 14)
    - Governing Board meeting minutes 1963-1985 (Box 14)
    - Michigan Conventions 1979-1982 (Box 14)
    - National Conventions 1980-1982 (Box 14)
    - Legislation: memoranda to members, correspondence, and other materials relating to proposed state and national legislation 1981-1984 (Box 14)
    - Letters to members of Congress and related 1981-1988 (Box 14)
    - Reports and other materials, arranged by organization office 1983-1986 (Box 14)
    - National Governing Board and various state chapters material 1982-1985 (Box 14)
    - Memos to area representatives 1981 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1980-1982, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Honors and Awards Committee 1966-1975 (Box 14)
  - Michigan Council of Administrators of Special Education (Michigan CASE)
    (division within Michigan CEC)
    - Constitution, memoranda, and other materials 1985-1988 (Box 14)
- Michigan Federation Chapters of the Council for Exceptional Children
  - History of the organization and related (Box 15)
  - Directories (Box 15)
  - Policy Handbook 1982 (Box 15)
  - Newsletters 1958-1992, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - State Convention programs and related 1962-1991 (scattered dates), 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Saginaw Valley Chapter #231
    - Minute book 1953-1981 (Box 15)
    - Audrey Kilts record book 1976-1982 (Box 15)
    - Constitution and miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Various records
    - Annual business meeting 1991 (Box 15)
    - Annual convention national organization, Detroit, Mich. 1983 (Box 15)
    - Various reports, news releases, memoranda 1960s-1988 (Box 15)
- Michigan Association of Administrators of Special Education (MAASE)
  - Administrative Handbook (Box 16)
  - Record books 1967-1979, 7 binders (Box 16)
    (include minutes, correspondence, membership material)
  - Lists of officers 1989-1990 (Box 16)
  - Executive secretary candidates (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
- Other organizations
  - Michigan School for the Blind publications (Box 17)
  - Statewide Communication and Dissemination System (SCADS)
    - Statewide Newsletter 1978-1984, 1991-1993, 1 folders; 3 binders (Box 18)
  - Citizens Alliance to Uphold Special Education (CAUSE)
    - Record book 1985 (Box 18)
  - Physically Impaired Association of Michigan (PIAM)
    (more commonly known as PAM or the PAM Assistance Center)
    - Record book containing newsletters and other mailings; also resource material 1983-1985, 1 folder; 1 binder (Box 19)
  - Statewide Technical Assistance Network in Special Education (STANSE) Initial Report 1975-1976 (Box 19)
- Published material
  - Local planning and instructional manuals
    - Berrien County Intermediate School District (Box 20)
    - Vocational Education Special Education Planning, Lansing School District (Box 20)
    - Muskegon Area Intermediate School District 1970 (Box 20)
    - Strategies and Techniques for Mainstreaming, Monroe County Intermediate School District (Box 20)
    - Special Education Administrative Application for Microcomputers, Genesee Intermediate School District (Box 20)
    - Special Education Administrative Manual January 1965 (compiled by Michigan Association of County Special Education Administrators (Box 20)
- Published material
  - Michigan Dept of Education
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - 1958 (Box 21)
    - 1963 (Box 21)
    - 1964 (Box 21)
    - 1965 (Box 21)
    - 1966, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - 1967, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - 1968, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - 1969, 7 folders (Box 21)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 21)
    - 1970, 6 folders (Box 21)
    - 1971, 6 folders (Box 21)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 21)
    - 1972, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - 1972, 4 folders (Box 22)
    - 1973, 6 folders (Box 22)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 22)
    - 1974, 5 folders (Box 22)
    - 1975 (Box 22)
    - 1976 (Box 22)
    - 1977, 10 folders (Box 22)
    - 1978, 4 folders (Box 23)
    - 1980, 4 folders (Box 23)
    - 1981, 5 folders (Box 23)
    - 1982, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - 1983, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - 1984 (Box 23)
    - 1986, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - 1987 (Box 23)
    - 1988 (Box 23)
    - 1990, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - 1991, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - 1992, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - 1994, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - 1995 (Box 23)
    - 1996 (Box 23)
  - Brochures, reports, workshops, conferences from various state, county and local agencies (Box 24)